Guide to The Edge collection of digital photographs AD.MC.021
Akkasah: Photography Archive (NYU Abu Dhabi)
The Edge
2014-2016
Akkasah: Photography Archive (NYU Abu Dhabi)
AD.MC.021
1 Terabytes
Arrangement
The collection was processed the way it was received.
Philip Cheung
Philip Cheung is a Canadian photographer based in Los Angeles (previously in Toronto).
His photographs have been exhibited in galleries, museums and festivals across North America and Europe, such as The National Portrait Gallery (London, UK), Lumix Festival (Hanover, DE) and the Flash Forward Festival (Toronto, CA).
In 2011, Cheung was named one of PDN's 30 New and Emerging Photographers to Watch and he has been awarded research and production grants by the Canada Council for the Arts, Ontario Arts Council and the Toronto Arts Council. In 2016 he was selected for the Canadian Forces Artist Program by the Directorate History and Heritage to continue a series that examines the sub-culture in Canada's post-Afghanistan military.
Cheung has also been recognized by the Magenta Foundation, Communication Arts, Photo District News and American Photo. His work is held in the collection of Akkasah, Center for Photography at New York University Abu Dhabi, and has appeared in features and reviews in The British Journal of Photography, CNN, Boston Review and TIME among others.
Scope and Contents
The Edge is a contemporary look at the evolving coastal landscape of the United Arab Emirates. The cultural and social identity of the UAE is particularly tied to its coastline, which played a deciding role in the development of the nation. The coastline provides an income resource and a connection between the Emirates and the rest of the world; first through shipping trade, fishing, pearling, and currently through the exploration of the oil industry and tourism. This changing relationship between the traditional and modern usage of the coastal landscape creates the space that I explore.
Since the discovery of oil off the coast of Abu Dhabi over 50 years ago, the UAE's 1,300km coastline, along with its cities and towns, has undergone considerable changes. The country, nestled in a pocket of financial security is growing diverse in form and function, with industry, tourism, and recreation shifting the scale and rhythm of the natural and the built environment. The landscape of the Emirates is aesthetically influenced by decades of substantial development, migratory movement, and lifestyles of the people who build, support and engineer the country.
The Edge seeks to survey the way the coastal landscape reflects present day socioeconomic realities of the Emirates.
Conditions Governing Access
Materials are open without restrictions.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Collection received directly from creator, Philip Cheung, in 2017.
Digital Photographs; United Arab Emirates; Coast; Dubai, United Arab Emirates; Abu Dhabi, United Arab Emirates
- Lifeboats, Al Jaddaf, 2015 (Object AD-MC-021_ref1_m)
  Landscapes; Boats/Ships; Dubai, United Arab Emirates; Digital Photographs; Buildings; Construction; Architecture
- Bridge, Jebel Ali, 2014 (Object AD-MC-021_ref3_m)
  Dubai, United Arab Emirates; Landscapes; Bridges; Architecture; Digital Photographs
- Men eating, Fujairah, 2014 (Object AD-MC-021_ref4_m)
  Factories; Landscapes; Men; Food; Fujairah, United Arab Emirates; Digital Photographs
- Rooftop, Deira, 2016 (Object AD-MC-021_ref5_m)
  Digital Photographs; Architecture; Buildings; Dubai, United Arab Emirates; Houses
- Zayed and cruise ship, Khor Fakkan, 2014 (Object AD-MC-021_ref6_m)
  Sharjah, United Arab Emirates; Boats/Ships; Water; Khor Fakkan, United Arab Emirates; Mountains/Hills; Landscapes; Digital Photographs
- Friday, Fujairah, 2014 (Object AD-MC-021_ref7_m)
  Water; Men; Cars/Trucks; Animals; Horses; Fujairah, United Arab Emirates; Digital Photographs; Buildings; Transportation
- Corniche, Ajman, 2015 (Object AD-MC-021_ref8_m)
  Streets/Roads; Digital Photographs; Ajman, United Arab Emirates; Coast
- Burj Khalifa, Al Rams, Ras al-Khaimah, 2014 (Object AD-MC-021_ref9_m)
  Ras Al-Khaimah, United Arab Emirates; Digital Photographs; Streets/Roads; Statues/Sculptures; Flags; Burj Khalifa; Architecture; Buildings
- Palestine, The World Islands, Dubai, 2017 (Object AD-MC-021_ref10_m)
  Seas; Water; Digital Photographs; Buildings; Arabian/Persian Gulf; Swimming; Bathing Suits/Swimsuits; Women; Men; Dubai, United Arab Emirates
- Sphinx, Umm al-Quwain, 2015 (Object AD-MC-021_ref11_m)
  Umm Al-Quwain, United Arab Emirates; Water; Restaurants/bars; Digital Photographs; The Great Sphinx of Giza
- Roundabout, Khor Fakkan, 2014 (Object AD-MC-021_ref12_m)
  Sharjah, United Arab Emirates; Khor Fakkan, United Arab Emirates; Architecture; Landscapes; Digital Photographs; Streets/Roads; Street Lamps; Buildings
- Coffee truck, Al Bateen, 2014 (Object AD-MC-021_ref13_m)
  Men; Cars/Trucks; Food; Tea/Coffee; Motorcycles; Abu Dhabi, United Arab Emirates; Drinks/Beverages; Digital Photographs; Flags; Water; Transportation
- Housing Development, Khalifa City, 2017 (Object AD-MC-021_ref14_m)
  Abu Dhabi, United Arab Emirates; Buildings; Architecture; Digital Photographs; Houses
- Resort, Sharjah, 2015 (Object AD-MC-021_ref15_m)
  Hotels; Boats/Ships; Digital Photographs; Palm Trees; Swimming Pools; Water
- Sharjah Aquarium, Al Khan., 2015 (Object AD-MC-021_ref16_m)
  Sharjah, United Arab Emirates; Digital Photographs; Men; Women; Outdoors; Group Portraits; Water; Painted Backdrops; Museums; Boys; Girls; Children; Head Covers/Veils; Regional/National Dress; Facial Hair
- Beach, Umm al-Quwain, 2015 (Object AD-MC-021_ref17_m)
  Umm Al-Quwain, United Arab Emirates; Landscapes; Water; Men; Beaches; Digital Photographs
- Banquet, Khor Al Maqta, 2015 (Object AD-MC-021_ref18_m)
  Military/Soldiers; Men; Abu Dhabi, United Arab Emirates; Sheikh Zayed bin Sultan Al Nahyan; Digital Photographs; Royalty; Zayed bin Sultan Al Nahyan, Sheikh, 1918-2004
- Dubai Marina, Dubai, 2016 (Object AD-MC-021_ref19_m)
  Water; Landscapes; Digital Photographs; Dubai, United Arab Emirates; Buildings; Architecture; Ports; Boats/Ships
- Cricket, Al Silaa, Western Region, 2014 (Object AD-MC-021_ref20_m)
  Digital Photographs; Abu Dhabi, United Arab Emirates; Men; Sports; Landscapes
- Mountainside, Ar Rufaysah, 2014 (Object AD-MC-021_ref21_m)
  Outdoors; Sharjah, United Arab Emirates; Mountains/Hills; Digital Photographs
- Al Abrar Restaurant, Tarif, Western Region, 2017 (Object AD-MC-021_ref22_m)
  Abu Dhabi, United Arab Emirates; Digital Photographs; Restaurants/bars; Landscapes; Buildings
- Gulf Cement, Khor Khuwair, 2015 (Object AD-MC-021_ref23_m)
  Construction; Signs/Signposts; Digital Photographs; Ras Al-Khaimah, United Arab Emirates
- The Royal Residence Hotel, Umm al-Quwain, 2015 (Object AD-MC-021_ref24_m)
  Men; Restaurants/bars; Digital Photographs; Umm Al-Quwain, United Arab Emirates; Hotels
- Residence, Umm al-Quwain, 2015 (Object AD-MC-021_ref25_m)
  Umm Al-Quwain, United Arab Emirates; Buildings; Architecture; Construction; Digital Photographs
- Quarry, Al Hayl, 2015 (Object AD-MC-021_ref26_m)
  Construction; Fujairah, United Arab Emirates; Digital Photographs
- Old Town, Umm Al Quwain, 2015 (Object AD-MC-021_ref27_m)
  Lanterns/Lamps; Palm Trees; Streets/Roads; Umm Al-Quwain, United Arab Emirates; Digital Photographs; Street Lamps
- Slow Down, Al Sila, Western Region, 2017 (Object AD-MC-021_ref28_m)
  Abu Dhabi, United Arab Emirates; Signs/Signposts; Digital Photographs; Construction
- Finjan Cafe, Fujairah, 2014 (Object AD-MC-021_ref29_m)
  Shops; Fujairah, United Arab Emirates; Food; Water; Cars/Trucks; Digital Photographs; Transportation; Buildings
- Security Guard, Saadiyat Island, 2014 (Object AD-MC-021_ref30_m)
  NYU Abu Dhabi; Abu Dhabi, United Arab Emirates; Digital Photographs; Men; Individual Portraits; Workers
- Breakwater, Abu Dhabi, 2015 (Object AD-MC-021_ref31_m)
  Buildings; Architecture; Men; Abu Dhabi, United Arab Emirates; Digital Photographs
- Palace, Umm Al-Quwain, 2014 (Object AD-MC-021_ref32_m)
  Digital Photographs; Streets/Roads; Umm Al-Quwain, United Arab Emirates; Forts/Castles; Palaces; Buildings
- Car accident, Al Badiyah, 2014 (Object AD-MC-021_ref33_m)
  Streets/Roads; Men; Fujairah, United Arab Emirates; Digital Photographs; Regional/National Dress; Street Lamps; Regional/National Dress; Crowds; Street Lamps
- Access road, Al Hayl, 2015 (Object AD-MC-021_ref34_m)
  Fujairah, United Arab Emirates; Digital Photographs; Outdoors; Streets/Roads; Mountains/Hills; Landscapes; Streets/Roads
- Extraction, Fujairah, 2014 (Object AD-MC-021_ref35_m)
  Men; Fujairah, United Arab Emirates; Digital Photographs; Water; Cars/Trucks; Transportation
- The Union, Sharm, 2015 (Object AD-MC-021_ref36_m)
  Flags; Mountains/Hills; Landscapes; Outdoors; Fujairah, United Arab Emirates; Digital Photographs
- Host Palace, Sharjah., 2015 (Object AD-MC-021_ref37_m)
  Digital Photographs; Architecture; Buildings; Women; Men; Hotels; Sharjah, United Arab Emirates; Group Portraits; Children; Picnic; Palm Trees
- Ferry Port, Jabal Al Dhanna, Western Region, 2014 (Object AD-MC-021_ref38_m)
  Cars/Trucks; Boats/Ships; Water; Ports; Abu Dhabi, United Arab Emirates; Digital Photographs; Boats/Ships; Transportation; Buildings
- Dubai Metro, Jebel Ali, 2017 (Object AD-MC-021_ref39_m)
  Railways; Trains; Dubai, United Arab Emirates; Digital Photographs; Transportation
- Al Naham Picnic Boat, Khor Fakkan, 2015 (Object AD-MC-021_ref40_m)
  Water; Flags; Boats/Ships; Sharjah, United Arab Emirates; Digital Photographs; Khor Fakkan, United Arab Emirates; Outdoors; Women; Men
- Jumeirah Beach Residence, Dubai, 2016 (Object AD-MC-021_ref41_m)
  Buildings; Architecture; Dubai, United Arab Emirates; Digital Photographs
- Labour housing, Ghalilah, 2014 (Object AD-MC-021_ref42_m)
  Water; Ras Al-Khaimah, United Arab Emirates; Digital Photographs; Buildings; Workers; Coast; Mountains/Hills
- Yellow Honda, Al Jeer, 2014 (Object AD-MC-021_ref43_m)
  Ras Al-Khaimah, United Arab Emirates; Cars/Trucks; Digital Photographs; Buildings; Signs/Signposts; Outdoors; Transportation
- Jumeirah Public Beach, Dubai, 2016 (Object AD-MC-021_ref44_m)
  Men; Beaches; Dubai, United Arab Emirates; Digital Photographs; Group Portraits; Workers; Mosques; Religious Sites; Buildings
- Al Sultan Tailoring, Fujairah, 2014 (Object AD-MC-021_ref45_m)
  Fujairah, United Arab Emirates; Regional/National Dress; Shops; Digital Photographs
- Sandstorm, Tarif, Western Region, 2017 (Object AD-MC-021_ref46_m)
  Digital Photographs; Outdoors; Landscapes; Deserts; Abu Dhabi, United Arab Emirates
- IDEX, Abu Dhabi, 2015 (Object AD-MC-021_ref47_m)
  Water; Women; Men; Military/Soldiers; Airplanes; Digital Photographs; Abu Dhabi, United Arab Emirates
- Battle Park, Ghantoot, 2017 (Object AD-MC-021_ref48_m)
  Sports; Abu Dhabi, United Arab Emirates; Digital Photographs
- Parking lot, Jumeirah Beach Residence, 2015 (Object AD-MC-021_ref49_m)
  Women; Men; Dubai, United Arab Emirates; Digital Photographs; Workers
- Night Club, Dubai, 2017 (Object AD-MC-021_ref50_m)
  Musicians; Women; Men; Musical Instruments; Restaurants/bars; Alcohol; Hotels; Dubai, United Arab Emirates; Digital Photographs
- National Day, Sufouh Beach, 2014 (Object AD-MC-021_ref51_m)
  Women; Men; Beaches; Fireworks; Burj Al Arab; Dubai, United Arab Emirates; Digital Photographs